Bui: [loud crackling in background] June 26 2010
at 12:20 ... am... 12:20pm... Byron Sonne ...
my name's Detective Bui, badge numbers 8650.
[opens door]
Byron, come on in.
Byron: Yes sir.
Bui: How are you doing?
Byron: Not good, sir.
Bui: Not good?
Byron: Well, you guys've took my wife.
Bui: OK... For you, the situation has remained the same.
There's no new charges, so I'm not here to advise you
of any new charges.
You're scenario's the same as before. You understand
what you're still under arrest for, right?
Byron: Yeah, I think.
Bui [sits on desk]: And those rights I explained to you
back at 13 division... And we talked the other day...
Nothing's changed for you, OK?
[Byron nods]
You understand that you're in a police facility?
Byron: Yes, sir.
Bui: And that everything we do and say is being monitored?
Bui: OK... So, I wanted to tell you personally that we
arrested Kristen and that she is here on two counts
that are named on your information, and those counts are
possession of a weapon and possession of an explosive device.
And I think it's important that we talk about this a little
bit today.
Because it's going to impact your family,
and the well being of your family from here on in.
And you remember I talked to you before about consequences?
Byron: Yes, sir.
I talked to you before about the impact the scenario you've
gotten yourself involved in, as we move forward,
and there might be a reasonable explanation for this scenario,
and you talked a lot about us trying to trick you up
in an interview and get you to admit stuff... But I'm going
to read you something, and it's significant,
and it's significant for you,
but mostly it's significant for Kristen, OK?
Byron [hoarse]: OK.
Bui: Will you hear me out?
Byron: I will hear you out. I may not respond, but --
Bui: And that's no problem. Today, I know today
you've talked to you're lawyers a lot, and I know
today is not going to be, like, the big interview
where I get, heh, the mad confession.
But I want to read you something.
And it's important for you to understand.
I'm going to be giving this to you in court...
[Bui gets up and crosses room]
Do you know who the RCMP are?
Byron: Yes sir.
Bui: The RCMP have a technical section that's far
better than the Toronto Police technical section.
And that's why their name's on here. We, in fact,
consult them on some of this.
I have some more stuff that I'm going to show you,
on you that the RCMP have.
Byron: OK.
Bui: This is an investigation report.
It's done by the open source... I'm sure they
explain it to you here... [crouches, holds out paper]
open source criminal intelligence section.
So they have the ability to go in to the Internet,
and the deep web, and pull up stuff that you and I have posted:
Facebook, links that we have done, OK?
And back in February, Kristen posted something. She said:
"If you blow up our house, I will be really, really, mad.
Also, thanks for asking to use my stuff. At least I get to
read about your transgressions. You make me smile."
It seems like an innocuous comment but in the totality
of everything, where we have explosive material
-- maybe you're saying not an explosive device,
[Bui slides over chair, sits] but explosive material,
in your home [slides chair right beside Byron], this is
what we call evidence that she had care and control of that.
She had knowledge of this, Byron.
This is a problem for her and we can't ignore that.
Do I think that, two years down the line...
This is going to effect her bail today.
We were talking, to her lawyer, really nice guy
named Howard Rugal. I've dealt with Howard before.
You can ask your lawyers to ask Howard, I'm a reasonable
detective. I've dealt with Howard, Mr. Rugal, many times before.
The Crown is a reasonable man. We've been engaged in a
conversation about fashioning a bail, a bail plan
that everyone's comfortable with, society will be happy with,
the police investigator will be happy with,
and that the courts will be happy with, to get her out.
I got this report this morning, honest to you,
I got this this report this morning.
After I'd spoke with mister Rugal last night.
And that comment causes a problem.
And she won't talk with me. I understand that.
You don't want to talk, and I understand that.
But is there a reasonable explanation for this?
Byron: Yes, but I [won't?] talk to you.
Bui: There's a reasonable explanation but
you're not willing to give what that reasonable
might have been? Today when
she's going up for bail?
Byron: It was a harmless joke, sir.
... I won't talk.
[Bui passes paper]
Bui: Here you go, take a look at that.
Tons of people are posting stuff in the
Toronto Star about you. Tons of people.
Tons of people are on redtag, and redline,
posting stuff.
Some of them, saying that you're critical
of the whole circus, blah, blah, blah.
[shuffles through papers]
=== Block 2 (5-10min)
=== Block 3 (10-15min)
=== Block 4 (15-20min)
=== Block 5 (20-25min)
=== Block 6 (25-30min)
=== Block 7 (30-35min)
=== Block 8 (35-40min)
=== Block 9 (40-45min)
=== Block 10 (45-50min)
BYRON: It is realistic.
BUI: I've been involved in trials so many times
before where like, guys get like,
three dudes, they've known each other since high school
one of them's a bad ass, one of them's maybe got
a little bit of a record, one of them's just a
joe that works at McDonald's,
and they get pulled over by the police and there's
two 45 caliber handguns under the seat.
All of them get charged.
All of them had access to it.
The driver especially gets charged. What if the
driver was the dude that actually had the legitimate
job working at McDonald's? When we come in to talk
to them, we say, man up, save a brother here,
save your friend. Man up for once.
And... so many people, I believe, make the mistake
of saying, "We're going to see what evidence you have,
we're gonna beat this."
BYRON: If it was between me and you, and I knew
that you were the Crown, and I know what you would
do, then I might take a different course.
But I can't trust what they're gonna do in there to me.
BUI: Who's they?
BYRON: The Crown. And all the other people lining up,
you're just one guy who might mean well, but I don't
really know that your weight carries all that much.
BUI: But keep in mind, I am the guy, I am the officer
in charge of these charges.
BYRON: Yeah, yeah, but you're not the Crown attorney,
and he can piss away anything you promise.
BUI: And you're correct there.
BYRON: That's why I have to wait for my lawyer to
hear these ideas.
BUI: OK, what happens when they put the officer
in charge up on the stand to go through the case.
That's going to be me, right.
Would you rather hear from me, one day down the line,
could be two years from now, you're sitting in
Maplehurst for two years, would you rather hear,
one day down the line, "I've talked to Byron a
number of times over the last year.
I've done an extensive investigation, we've analyzed
his computer, we've analyzed his cell phone records,
his Visa bills like you suggest, we went and pulled
videos at the Home Depot and stuff, we went and pulled
this and we've done our job.
We've done the job that we get paid to do, and
we get trained to do.
And at the end of the day, I think that Byron wasn't
really going to set off the bomb, but he had a bomb
in his house, your honour, that's my opinion.
Would you rather hear me say that or would you rather
hear me say
Byron put together a bomb,
and Byron was going to use that bomb during G20.
That's what I believe.
And he had all the tools, and the knowledge,
and the equipment.
BYRON: But you don't believe that.
You can't tell me you'd go up there and lie just to
spite me because I didn't plead out early like you wanted.
BUI: I'm not saying it's a lie and i'm not saying it's
because you didn't plead out early.
I'm saying think to what you know we're going to find out.
I'm honest when I say that Byron I think you're a smart guy.
Do you think I'm a bumbling buffoon?
BYRON: No, of course not.
BUI: Like one of those Keystone Kops in the old TV shows?
BYRON: No, they're so high up in the government they
don't really need to obey the law. They have their own
separate bunch of things...
If all of a sudden they feel like this looks good, let's
bring this guy in on a security ticket,
my rights don't matter anymore.
BUI: Byron, I don't think it's ever going to get to the stage
where anyone brings you anywhere on a security ticket.
And I promise you, that if anyone tries to, I am going
to fight tooth and nail to beat it, to have you be at a
normal facility, where we can do this, and where you are
subject to the regular rules of law in Canada.
From me as a man, OK.
BYRON: OK
BUI: But that's not to say that those people aren't
going to be looking at you.
BYRON: I know they will. I know they're probably already.
BUI: Well, I'm showing you this, brother. I'm being straight
up with you, right? People have given me information.
People are trying to help me here. If there's something
I don't have, I'm going to ask people to try to help me get it.
I'm just a lowly organized crime detective from Toronto,
who has been given this case to manage.
BYRON: Yeah, but, twenty years from now you might be
the you know, [ui] running the show.
Not lowly for that long.
BUI: Because you asked me before, I'm going to explain these
police powers that people are talking about, the media.
The province of Ontario, back like 10 years ago, elected
something called like the Public Works Act.
And what the Public Works Act says is that anything built
for the public by the government... like a highway, and a highway
is like almost every road and every major thoroughfare in Toronto.
Like, you know how Dundas is highway 5?
BYRON: Oh, ok, right.
BUI: Yonge Street is what, highway 11, something like that?
BYRON: Yup.
BUI: Those are all provincial highways. The courthouse,
Queen's Park, different government buildings, they're considered
public works.
They don't use the term buildings, they use the term works,
so it's more all encompassing.
BYRON: Understood.
BUI: When you're on a public work, you are subjected to
identifying yourself, consenting to a search by the police,
and it's the provincial legislation that allows us to search
people coming into a provincial courthouse.
It's a public building, it's accessed by the public, freedom
of the courts, we're allowed to unless there's a publication ban,
we're allowed, sorry, unless it's a closed court, the media is
allowed in, they're allowed to report on what happens in the
court, unless there's a publication ban.
But what gives us the powers to search people and identify them
coming in is the Public Works Act.
So, they looked at the construction for G20 and they thought
here's this government-funded, government-built security perimeter
for a government event.
And these fences are mainly built on public roads that are
already deemed public works. So, can we just go ahead
and start IDing poeple?
Yeah, we probably could, I don't think we
BYRON: Well, fucking brilliant.
BUI: Hold on, the chief wanted to go the extra mile and say,
well listen, why don't we have the fence and its construction
designated as a public work temporarily.
How do we go about doing that?
And it was actually quite simple.
We didn't have to go to the provincial legislature, a letter
had to be signed by the Lieutenant-Governor in council, so they
went to the LG with the letter, saying can you designate the
security perimeter around these secure sites as a public work.
And the governor said well, hey, it's on a public work
already, it's on a highway, it's protecting a public event,
I'll designate it for a week as a public work, specifically the fence
So people are all up in arms that this secret law was passed,
I'm telling you, Byron, that's not the case.
BYRON: But it does sound funny, because the G20 isn't really
a public event.
BUI: But it's for public officials. Just like some meetings in
Queen's Park aren't public events, some are closed meetings.
But we could stop someone in Queen's Park.
BYRON: But because it's on behalf, on behest of the public that
elected you, that sort of qualifies it.
That's pretty damn clever actually.
BUI: I think it's pretty clever too.
And you know, there's gonna be poeple who are going to challenge
the Charter ramifications of it.
BYRON: They're already working on it,
I think I saw it on the news.
BUI: And I knew about it as a sergeant on the road,
and I knew that it was a very tenuous thing to have to direct your
officers if they were ever really pressed for getting a guy's ID,
to use that Act on them if they were standing on the highway.
There's other reasons why we can ask people for identification
and you know, do a pat down search for your safety,
and we really shy away from people doing that under the
Public Works Act, but many of us knew about it before.
It's nothing new, it's been around for like over 10 years.
So, it's funny, the Toronto Star published that we snuck this
legislation in and the next line, "but it's been around for 10 years"
I felt like emailing the reporter and saying did you really read
what you're writing here? You're contradicting yourself!
BYRON: That's the Star, they're a little lefty that way.
BUI: If we're gonna move forward, one day, you and I, Byron,
with this concept that yes, you're guilty of something, whatever
that might be... and maybe misadventures are the biggest issue here,
but do the elements support the offence of possession of an explosive?
Well, maybe.
Because we're going to have to do the testing, we're going to
have to put a package together that says yes, and it's going to
be a hard thing for you to argue against.
BYRON: I don't doubt that it will be successful.
BUI: And one day we're going to have to talk about a strategy,
you and I, your lawyer and the Crown. Like, OK, time for a
guilty plea, let's put this to bed.
I want you to think about that, OK.
I want you to think about it, and I'm going to come
and talk to you again.
Your lawyer's going to tell you, Byron, do not talk to
that detective Bui guy ever again, but every time I have
an opportunity or something new comes up, I'm going to
want to come and talk to you about it.
Because I want you to see how this case is growing and
growing and growing.
And how worse it might look for you.
But more specifically, if she wasn't part of it, how it's
gonna be bad for her.
And if it come to a stage where the Crown is reasonably
convinced that in the public's interest, maybe her charges
could be withdrawn, that would be a consideration for
another day down the line.
But that involves a commitment from all of us to come
with one solid story, ok?
BYRON: I've listened to what you've said, I am thinking
about it, but I do need to run things by my lawyer.
BUI: You ever go on redflageals.com?
BYRON: No, what is that?
BUI: It's like a forum, for Canada's hardest bargain
hunting community, for getting deals.
But people post on it.
Do you know this guy, Greg-o-mania?
BYRON: [ui]
BUI: He posted, "Well if his goal was to test the system
and see if he would get caught, looks like the government
passed the test with flying colours."
Could that have been a [ui]
Like this is some random dude that's blogged about you.
But i'm wondering, is this the same thing. Like, me as the
investigator, I've honstly turned my mind to this.
Was Byron willing to push the envelope so far that he was
trying to test the security apparatus and in the end, the
security apparatus beat him, it worked.
And is he really that unhappy about it?
That really, there's a system put in place to protect the
general public.
Maybe you don't agree with the G20, but you wanted to test
the system, and you did.
BYRON: I don't really honestly give that much of a shit about
what goes on at the G20 or the G8 to be honest.
BUI: I think it looks like you were testing the system.
BYRON: Can I talk to my lawyer about that?
BUI: Sure.
Just another [ui] if you need anything to talk
to your lawyer about.
Did you have access to reading these blogs and stuff
when you're in there?
BYRON: In where?
BUI: Do you have the internet in jail?
BYRON: No, [laughing]
BUI: Honestly, I don't know.
BYRON: No man, they change every day when we go into bed
at night. The TV volume down doesn't work, shit man they
make up rules as they go along there.
They're polite to me, don't get me wrong.
BUI: Right.
BYRON: I mean, I'm with a guy that's coming down off this
fucking methadone, which isn't cheerful.
But I'm also in with the chainsaw guy, who got busted at
[unintellible] security thing.
BUI: [laughs] What's his story?
BYRON: He was coming back from fixing his cottages, or some
shit like that, or some property or something and he parked
his car downtown to take his dog for a walk.
And then, all hell broke loose.
Sister's taking care of his dog, but like I saw him on the
news, and there was, what do you call, a bow and arrow
BUI: A crossbow?
BYRON: Oh, crossbow.
BUI: A crossbow, and that's a prohibited device in
Canada too, I think.
BYRON: No, I don't think it is. Not a crossbow.
Small crossbows are. I think miniature handheld ones
that you can conceal are, I think, but I think the
fullsize ones are still legal.
Whether you need an FAC or a PAL or whatever it's called,
I'm not sure, but I think it's still legal.
There's a hunting shop, I've seen hunting
shops that carry them.
BUI: Crossbows? Are you sure about that?
BYRON: I think so.
BUI: Ah, maybe. When we release people on bail conditions
for weapons, it's always like not to be in possession of
an FAC, firearms, ammunition, and then they always list
crossbows and explosives, and that always kind of makes me chuckle.
Like, why they throw crossbows in there?
BYRON: Oh yeah, and then there was a whole bunch of gasoline
generators, chainsaws and shit like that.
He was like, what the hell, you know
BUI: This guy [ui] writes, "I've heard that in the US they
track purchases and if, for example, you go to Home Depot
and buy, as an example, liquid Drano plus muriatic acid plus
chemical X and a red light goes off at a monitoring station,
then they track you.
I don't believe this stuff."
BYRON: Oh, I think they probably do down there.
They're crazy.
BUI: "They are precursor chemicals to more interesting chemicals.
My opinion, is that only retards would buy all of their supplies
at one place and use a credit card to buy their supplies."
Reason I read that to you is you brought up your credit card story.
Did you use your credit cards to purchase all this stuff?
BYRON: Yes.
BUI: So here's something you mentioend before.
The sulfuric acid you got--not sulfuric acid--
the ammonium nitrate
isn't the fertilizer type, it's the type from the
cold packs that you bought.
Why would you?
Don't you think, Byron that
BYRON: Because you can't go and buy a bag of ammonium
nitrate anymore.
BUI: Why not?
BYRON: Because you need to buy them in like 50 pound
things and it's just hard as hell, and I don't know any
stores that actually sell it because they're all afraid
of being listed as terrorists.
I didn't even know it was still sold in Canada until I
heard about that dude up in Niagara Region with 60 bags
or something.
BUI: So when did you buy those, the cold packs?
BYRON: Couple months ago? Month ago?
BUI: Where?
BYRON: Shopper's Drug Mart
BUI: Which one?
BYRON: The one up by
Eglinton
and Spadina?
Eglinton and Chaplin?
BUI: With your Visa?
BYRON: Probably. either that or my bank card.
BUI: And I ask these questions, I know you're thinking,
holy cow he's going to go there.
Of course I'm going to go there, Byron.
I'm going to pull video tapes to see you buying it.
but stuff that you bought on your credit card shows that you
weren't hiding what you were doing.
But I still have to go and find out.
BYRON: No, I know.
BUI: So I still have to ask you these questions.
BYRON: Absolutely.
BUI: And I appreciate you telling me, because I know
your lawyer will tell you
"Byron, don't tell him you bought cold packs to get
ammonium nitrate out of them!"
I know he'll say that.
But it's important for me.
I need to put the big picture together.
And if that big picture clears you, then that's great.
If that big picture says holy shit, Byron, you need
to man up and take some responsibility here for some
really stupid behaviour, then maybe that's the option.
Or you shut your mouth and you let us run our trial
and you see what a judge does with it. Right?
BYRON: Believe me, I'm somewhat leaning towards your
position but I just need to talk to the lawyer.
BUI: For sure. And you know that it's just an example
I'm throwing out there, right?
And it's based on my experience with the justice system,
it's based on my experience with putting hundreds of people
before the courts.
And in my preference, most of them on good charges with good
evidence and a lot for violent offences, or drug offences, right.
Not the chicken shit stuff.
So, I've got my job to do, Byron, and as we move along,
you'll see that I'm accumulating evidence and giving
it to your lawyer, giving it to the crown,
saying we've interviewed these people,
this is what we're seeing, and allways being open
and honest with you about this.
The secret investigation is over, everything I do now
is disclosable.
You get all my notes, and I'll tell you,
I'll bring stuff to you.
BYRON: How badly was my house damaged? Who's looking after it?
BUI: We're turning the key over to your lawyer today...
or to Kristen's lawyer, but I think your lawyer wants it.
The damage, we videotaped everything before we went out
and before we did our search and I don't think there's
a lot of damage.
I never went in the scene once we started the search.
For continuity, I stay out.
I had an officer there, a guy who works for me the whole time.
Making sure that no one went in the building that should not
have gone in there, other than our forensics people.
They're very respectful and professional about it.
BYRON: What can be done for bail today?
BUI: Well I dunno. I think your lawyer is going to
talk to you about a strategy today for where you go
for your bail, what you should do for your bail.
But I think Kristen wants to run her bail hearing.
And that...this stuff is going to cause a problem for her, man.
Honestly, it is. I'm not being.. I'm not...
BYRON: She has nothing to do with any of this.
You gotta realize that, she is nothing to do with any of this.
BUI: But prescriptive possession is the knowledge
you possess it, and I'll give you an example.
I start accumulating illegal firearms in my house and
my wife knows they're there.
And one day Toronto Police come and kick my door down and
do a search warrant, and they seize something [ui]
BYRON: Where's that picture from anyway?
BUI: Is that you?
BYRON: Yeah.
BUI: I have no idea. It looks like you're wearing
a rugby or a soccer jersey.
BYRON: Danish soccer jersey, but they're out of
the World Cup now, so...
BUI: Are you Danish?
BYRON: Well, my dad is. Other side's Irish.
Like third generation, potato famine, [ui]
BUI: What I was saying before was if she knew about it,
she knew it was there, then she's guilty by prescriptive
possession as well. That's a problem that's Kristen
gonna have, I'm not going to lie to you.
You know, all that other stuff. The dealing with [ui]
considering the potato gun like a launcher that could cause
grievous bodily harm or death, it's classified as a weapon,
that stuff is still all there, right, but it's the issue of...
boil it down to the big issue is the explosives.
That's the big issue. possession is prescriptive.
You live in a home together. I pulled the land title,
it's in both your names.
Obviously you live there, neighbours are going
to say you live there.
Tons of evidence in there that says you live there.
BYRON: Oh, of course.
BUI: You're admitting that she lives there with you, right,
so... How do we get past that for her?
We try to fashion a bail, that is realistic,
that society can be happy with, that her lawyers
are happy with, that your lawyers are happy with,
that the JP is happy with, that the Crown is happy with.
And I don't know if that's possible today with
that comment that was found in open source.
I don't know.
BYRON: Her lawyer I imagine will be able to see all this stuff?
BUI: Absolutely. You both will get a copy.
Truth be told, honestly, I just got a copy of it
this morning. They were working on her last night,
they gave me a copy this morning. I didn't know about
it before, that's why I never brought it up with
your lawyer or talked to you about it.
I knew about it this morning, I've had to let
the Crown know, that's the way disclosure works. I'm
letting you read it; I'm going to let her and
her lawyers have it, too.
Her disclosure I can share with you;
your disclosure I can share with her.
BYRON/BUI: [unintelligible]
BYRON: Does that mean her lawyers are like co-counsel or...
BUI: No, my assumption is they're going to run very
separate here. Because her lawyer, in my opinion, is
going to do like, "Wow, we got to insulate Kristen
from that crazy behaviour that her husband was engaging in."
BYRON: Yeah.
BUI: "Maybe it was behind her back," right? And he would
love to say it was. But that blog proves differently,
does it not?
BYRON: I don't think it does, but I know they'll
make a case for that saying that it does
BUI: You need to come up with a strategy to help her
with that. And I'm kind of fresh out of ideas, like,
I really am. The wave cannon, that's realistic, but,
see, the problem here is that issue about the wave cannon
and when that conversation
might have occurred, and when we might be able to get
receipts for all the chemicals that you bought, and
maybe all those chemical purchases started at a certain
date...and if that comment in February pre-dated the
chemical purchases, then maybe that's a reasonable
explanation that that comment she definitely was
referring to the wave cannon, because we have
evidence that proves Byron wasn't buying those chemicals until when.
BYRON: You won't be able to find that evidence. I didn't
buy any of that stuff until... fuck, I can't even remember.
[pause]
April? Maybe.
BUI: All of it? Or some of it?
BYRON: Well, there'd probably be some things, like...
because when I was starting to grow crystals and stuff,
I started building the dryers and stuff first so that I
could evaporate the liquid and get nice big crystals to
give to people as presents and stuff like that but...
...I'm trying to go through the cabinet
and everything that was in there...
BUI: [ui]
BYRON: I might have got some of the camping tablets, like
the stove tablets, the dry fuel tablets, in the winter,
because you know, I'm trying to put together like a camping
kit and stuff for the summer.
So that would probably be the only thing I could think of.
BUI: So for example, thinking off the top of my head,
if we can, if I can collect evidence that says, "Look
Byron purchased a camp...with dry..."
What's it called? Dry fuel?
BYRON: Tri-oxine [ui] tablets.
BUI: OK, so camping tablets that are tri-oxine.
BYRON: Yeah, whatever you guys are
calling hexamine or something.
BUI: So that's also what it is? Hexamine?
BYRON: Yeah, it's part of both, I think,
a little of both in there.
BUI: So Byron purchased hexamine in Christmas.
And then Kristen made that post in February, and
Byron bought no other chemicals that could be combined
to make an explosive device until April, then it is
impossible for that comment to be in relation to explosives.
She was talkig about the microwave gun, maybe somehow
we can prove that you were using the microwave gun in that
timeframe? That's the kind of stuff I'm talking about as
a strategy to help her.
BYRON: You should be able to find all that.
BUI: What about the proof that the wavegun was being
experimented on in that time, that that was what she was
referring to? How do we get to that?
BYRON: Shit, I deleted that out of my YouTube account. But...
BUI: Ok, well, we have your computer and I'm going to
look for times that you uploaded YouTube videos about
the wave cannon.
So did you upload YouTube videos of you
deploying the wave cannon?
BYRON: Yes.
BUI: Around what months would those be in?
BYRON: I can't, I can't really remember. That would
be much earlier in the year, there might have still
been snow on the ground...it might have even been
last year.
No, because if that comment was [ui] the 14th, it must
have been January or February..
BUI: 14th of February... it was in 2009?
You remember? [ui]... [Bui flips papers] Yeah, it was
February 25th, 2009, so well over a year ago.
Ok, so that's a little bit better.
BYRON: OK.
BUI: So you're trying to tell me, straight up, you did
not purchase any of the chemicals to be used in making
an explosive device until after April of 2010.
BYRON: I can't give you exact dates because my memory's
a little fried, I'm gong through hell right now, but
I swear to God I can't remember purchasing anything like
that stuff before Christmas, you know... for sure, definitely
before Christmas, I'm trying to think of any of these things...
You know
Shit
April, May...
The earliest I can think of is March.
BUI: Ok.
BYRON: I could be wrong. I don't want you to sit here
and come back and say, "Well Byron I found something in
February blah blah blah" and maybe say I'm lying but to
the best of my knowledge I honest to God don't remember
buying anything earlier than, you know, four months ago or
something like that.
BUI: Byron, it's, I'd love to keep talking to you, and
I'm going to talk to you again, I'm telling you that
right now. I know your lawyer is like "Do not talk to
Detective Bui when he shows up" and you know what, I don't
mind if I come here and I just show
you, look, here's some stuff we found,
like help me out here...
and really, Kristen can be released, and we can start
working on strategy for you, that would be my preference.
My preference doesn't always go in court.
I'll still bring you stuff to look at; you don't
even have to say anything to me if you don't want,
OK, I won't be insulted.
But I want to give you some time, court [unintellgible]
up at 2 o'clock, we're gonna have to deal with the Kristen
bail matter, I'm sure your lawyer's going to want to talk
to you about a strategy for bail.
BYRON: Anything you can do to help my wife,
sir, she's everything to me.
BUI: OK, well, I think we made some ground. Because
you've given me some proof that, and we're gonna have
to research on where you purchased this stuff.
BYRON: You know, I can't think of anything I bought
with cash. You can pull my bank card numbers, my Visa
card numbers, although I think it's a shared number with
Kristen so hopefully that won't fucking blow up in her face.
BUI: So what, tell me mostly where you
purchased this stuff. What stores?
BYRON: Um, Home Depot in Leaside.
BUI: OK.
BYRON: Do you know the one I'm talking about it?
It's near Eglinton and Laird.
BUI: Yup. I know exactly where it is, I go to the same one.
BYRON: Oh, really? You ever notice that
there's all kinds of gay dudes there?
[Bui laughs]
BYRON: Is that the gay Home Depot, because they
all come from downtown?
BUI: I'm not sure.
BYRON: I find it funny... check it out when you're
in there next time, you might notice it.
BUI: I will, OK, Home Depot, Eglinton and Laird...
BYRON: The Canadian Tire up at Eglinton and Laird.
BUI: OK.
BYRON: Ah, jeez. Those are the two biggest.
That Shopper's Drug Mart...
BUI: That's for the cold packs?
BYRON: Yup. Up by Eglinton and...
Eglinton and Spadina? Eglinton and Chaplin?
BUI: Eglinton and Chaplin, oh.
BYRON: In between [ui] and Chaplin.
BUI: OK. Why those places? They're kind
of far from your house, right?
BYRON: No, not at all.. Oh, those.
Because I used to do
like tons of work, building in the Don Valley
over the years. You know, like fixing up [ui] trails,
clearing up garbage, making things safe... we call it
"fat kid proof" so no one breaks their neck and we get
sued and trails get torn up.
BUI: OK.
BYRON: Because it's really special in there, you can
even see deer in the Don Valley, it's really beautiful.
And those were always the two ones that were closest,
whether we need like screws or wood for building like
ramps and ladders and things like that, fixing stuff up.
So that was just for five-six years I've been working out
of the Don Valley and those are just the ones by habit I go to.
Also, I know the stores and I know where everything's
located and there's a good pizza place across the street.
Well, a crappy pizza place across the street,
but it's good.
BUI: [laughs] What's it called?
BYRON: Panzerotti 2-for-1, something like that.
BUI: Across from the Home Depot?
BYRON: Across from the Canadian Tire. And the Canadian
Tire has a good chip truck in the parking lot, too.
BUI: Good panzerottos there, or good pizza slices?
BYRON: I like the German pizza that they have there.
BUI: German pizza...
BYRON: And they also sell good French fries in the
Canadian Tire parking lot.
um, other store, other stores...
BUI: So everything was purchased with your bank card?
BYRON: Bank card or Visa. Don't think
I've ever done anything cash.
BUI: OK, and this is March, maybe Christmas,
and after; or March and after?
BYRON: Christmas and after, maybe March and after...
I can't, it's hard to remember some of these things.
BUI: OK.
BYRON: I mean I think there was, there might be one
other store... by Steeles and the 400, like a hydroponics
store. I bought a couple of chemicals there when I was
still trying to work on growing some plants.
I mean, not those kinds of plants...but seriously, I am
into growing my own food. You can stop my house and
see the corns and beans and stuff.
BUI: OK, you bought fertilizer?
BYRON: No, I bought the, what's that shit there...
The guy sold me stuff, potassium silicate, it's supposed to give
strong stalks, because I was sick of the corn bending over.
Um...and then the, um, what's that shit called
You use it for bleaching hair.
It was when I was going to do the first [ui] rocket...
You use a liquid fuel out of...hydrogen peroxide. Because
then it meant I didn't need any nasty chemicals or stuff
like that, I just use a liquid, and I could put it through a
platinum grid which wuld make steam and water, ntohing toxic.
But then I looked into how much platinum wire was, and it's
an arm and a fucking leg, so I gave up on that.
BUI: OK.
BYRON: I can't remember the name of the store.
BUI: You turn your mind to evidence that we
might come up with as the months go on that could
exonerate your wife, like communications between her
and you that didn't revolve around you purchasing
chemicals that could be used as explosives.
That's going to help her.
It's not going to help you, but I think you have
come to terms with some of this a little bit, and
maybe that's a good thing.
It's misguided misadventure, curiosity got the
better of you, whatever the case may be Byron.
You need to take some serious consideration into that.
BYRON: Absolutely.
BUI: Ok, I want to give you a chance to have adequate
time to talk to your counsel before this hearing. Court
never gets heard at 2 o'clock on the dot.
Take as much time as you need [ui] to take that time, OK.
I know we're ready to go with Kristen's bail hearing,
I know the Crown is going to talk about this posting that
she made to you, they're going to argue the legitimacy of
the source and blah blah blah, we're probably going to have
to get up on the stand and say where we got the information
from. But maybe running the bail hearing for her is not
the greatest idea, in light of this...but you would have
to talk to your lawyer about communicating with her lawyer
about that, right.
Because...you have one chance at bail, if that gets denied,
you go to Superior Court for a Superior Court bail review.
Expensive, more onerous, and it's the second kick at the can.
The first kick at the can is usually the best, but your
lawyers will explain this to you.
BYRON: OK.
BUI: That's been my experience as a detective, OK.
Byron, thanks. I'm going to come again, I'm telling you.
BYRON: Please, please do what you can for Kristen.
I couldn't live with myself if she gets shut away in some
hole for God knows how long.
BUI: OK. Think about what I talked to you today about,
talk to your lawyer about it. He's going to tell you
never to talk to me again, I'm still going to come,
I'm still going to show you stuff.
And just turn your mind to us trying to figure out if
she knew about what you were doing.
[Byron distracted by sensor]
Sorry, that's a little sensor there. What you were....
BYRON: Oh, I know...my father-in-law's company used
to make those. It was probably made by them.
BUI: Anyways, keep it in mind, OK. Good luck today.
BYRON: OK. Thank you.
BUI: OK, hang on just one second.
BYRON: If i get stuck in there, maybe I could have
a sweater? Just cause it's cold?
BUI: Yeah, we don't have prisoner clothing here, eh,
for warmth. What about back in Maplehurst?
OTHER OFFICER: Back at Maplehurst they will.
BUI: Byron, talk to them back at Maplehurst, OK?
That'll be the end of the interview, it's, 1:44.
I'm going to do a visual count for the camera so
we can try to marry up the audio and the video.
1 2 3 4 is a visual count.